Well, good morning, church.
Hope you guys are having a good morning so far.
Praise the Lord.
If you haven't had the privilege,
if I haven't had the privilege of meeting you,
it is not a privilege to meet me.
I'm sorry.
Maybe that was a Freudian slip.
I don't know what's going on on there.
But if we haven't had the privilege of meeting,
my name is Ryan,
and I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here.
Next weekend, we are going to be wrapping up
this very long summer series called
The Summer's Journey,
where we've been looking at the life,
teaching, ministry, and letters of the Apostle Paul.
I hope that this series has helped you
in your faith journey.
I hope we've learned some things about Paul's life
and his ministry that will help us
better understand his letters in their context.
Reading the Bible in its proper context
and applying it to our proper context
can be a challenging task.
I hope this has been helpful.
I hope you've seen the importance of approaching Paul's letters
as primarily, primarily his letters were pastoral,
encouragements, challenges to specific groups of people
and specific individuals, people who were struggling,
rather than these theological books
that were written specifically for us
to build our theology off of.
Our theology should be built off of
the application of what he was intending to communicate
to his original audience
and worked backwards from there.
And most, many theological camps claim to do this,
but it can be harder than it looks.
And so hopefully we've learned some of that
throughout this series.
Today, we're gonna finish up
a three-week kind of mini-series
we did within this series on Paul
and how Paul talks about salvation in three tenses.
Paul talks about salvation in the past tense,
in the present tense, in the future tense.
And he says that we were saved,
we are being saved, and we will be saved.
The illustration I used a couple weeks ago
was that of adoption, right?
There's a moment in time
when someone is adopted in the past.
It's a legal binding decision.
They've been adopted.
And in the present,
they're learning how to live in this new family
with new kind of systems and structures.
And then they will have a future inheritance
as a member of that family.
Last week, Nick used a similar illustration
about the nation of Israel through the Exodus, right?
Nick said there was a past salvation
from their slavery in Egypt.
And then there was a present salvation in the desert.
They were being saved from slavery.
And then their future salvation
was that of inheriting the promised land
as they crossed into the Jordan.
So that's kind of the three-week structure
that we've been following.
All three tenses of salvation are important to Paul.
But if you missed the last two weeks,
I've got good news for you.
The future tense salvation
is Paul's emphasis throughout all of his writings.
It is the focal point of salvation,
of the salvation narrative.
For Paul, it is in the future.
Dr. Brenda Colleen says it this way,
salvation for Paul is predominantly future.
So you picked the right week to be here.
All right, let's pray and get started.
Father, we are so grateful for this opportunity
to think about what salvation means for Paul
and therefore what implications it has on our lives.
God, I know that we all come in here
with different worries and fears and anxieties
and confusion and doubts and questions and unbelief.
Wherever we might be in the room this morning,
I pray that through your Holy Spirit and your word,
you would communicate exactly what you want us to hear,
that we would just be in an open posture to hear from you,
that your words would encourage and challenge
and draw us into a closer relationship with you
for your glory, for our good,
and for the good of our neighbors.
It's in Jesus' name I pray, amen.
Okay, I am gonna step out on what I think
is a very sturdy limb this morning
and say that every single one of us in this room
has experienced suffering.
Is that a fair statement?
Every single one of us in this room has faced suffering.
Many of us in this room this morning
are currently dealing with suffering.
We're struggling through a difficult situation
or circumstance in our life.
And if we personally aren't struggling,
we are probably in close relational proximity
to someone who is struggling or suffering.
We've all experienced suffering.
It's a regular occurrence on life.
On life, what am I looking to say there?
In life on earth, there we go.
And for those of us who have even had
a relatively smooth life,
who have escaped much possibility
and opportunity for suffering,
even if we've had a relatively comfortable life,
we know that deep down,
in the good times,
in the best times,
they don't truly fulfill us
or satisfy us to the longings of our heart.
C.S. Lewis summarizes this
in his chapter on hope and mere Christianity
when he says,
no, I'm summarizing C.S. Lewis,
so it's gonna sound less smart
than C.S. Lewis said it,
but he says,
no relationship,
no vacation,
he says holiday
because he's British,
no hobby,
no career,
it will never satisfy you
the way that you hope it might.
And he goes on to say,
and this is the part,
the cheeky part
that I really love,
he says,
and I'm talking about
the best possible ones.
He's not talking about
bad marriages,
bad vacations,
bad hobbies,
difficult careers.
He's saying,
even in the best of circumstances
in life on earth,
they often leave us wanting.
I'm getting ready to go on vacation,
and I already know
that about two days into vacation,
you know what I'm gonna be thinking about?
It ending.
I'm gonna be thinking about vacation ending,
like there's so much time
to enjoy the vacation,
and I am going to be thinking about it ending
because there is no vacation,
no career,
no hobby,
no relationship
that will satisfy
the deepest longings
of our soul.
Suffering,
our lives are full of it
from one degree or another,
and even when we avoid it,
the good times
still leaving us,
leave us feeling wanted.
Let's pray and go home.
I'm just kidding.
But I think
this is why Paul tends to focus
on future tense salvation
when he talks about salvation
because in my opinion,
and I think in Paul's opinion,
future salvation,
a proper understanding
of future salvation
is the only medicine
for our present sufferings.
This is where we're gonna be
in Romans chapter eight,
so if you have your Bibles
and you wanna go there,
one of Paul's most glorious texts
on the future salvation,
he says this,
Romans eight,
verse 18,
I consider
that our present sufferings
are not worth comparing
with the glory
that will be revealed
in us
in the future.
I consider
that our present sufferings
are not worthy
to be compared
to the future glory
that will be revealed.
This verse
is Paul's thesis
for his argument
in our passage today.
He says that present sufferings
of this world
are not worthy
to be compared
to the future glory
that will be revealed
when God's redemptive plan
for salvation
comes to its eternal conclusion
in the future.
This is what Paul has in mind
when he speaks of salvation
in the future tense.
And spoiler alert,
it's a lot better
than most of us think
when we think about
going to heaven
when we die.
We'll get there.
Don't worry.
I love how Paul phrases it.
He actually uses
a mathematical phrase
in the Greek.
Consider.
It literally is
a mathematical term.
He means,
I've done the calculations.
Right?
I've ran the equation.
I've put the sufferings
of the present world
on one side of the scale
and I've put
the weight of future glory,
of future salvation
on the other side
of the scale
and it's not even close.
The future salvation
wins out
over the present suffering.
I consider it.
It's not even worthy
to be compared.
And I know
what some of you in here
who have been,
who have suffered a lot
might be thinking.
Some of you
who are suffering
a lot right now
might be thinking,
well, that's easy
for him to say.
He's a famous guy
who wrote one third
of the New Testament.
He must have had
some kind of euphoric
intimacy with God.
Good thing we just spent
13 weeks studying
his life, right?
He was stoned
and left for dead.
He received 39 lashes
from the Romans
and the Jews.
He was shipwrecked
in and out of jail,
bit by a poisonous snake.
Anybody's suffering
compared to Paul's suffering?
Plus, he had a thorn
in his flesh
and in case you were thinking
that he had some direct
access to God
where he kind of got
this like special treatment,
he had a thorn
in his flesh
that he prayed,
not a physical thorn,
just in case you were picturing,
like, can't somebody
just take that out?
No.
We don't know exactly
what it is,
but he had something,
some deep trauma
that he was dealing
with in his life
and he prayed desperately
to God
to take it away
three times
and God very clearly
told him no.
This is the guy
who's telling us
that our present suffering
is not worthy
to be compared
to the future glory
of salvation.
Paul has suffered
more than most of us
could ever imagine
and yet he remains convinced
that the glory
to be revealed
in our future salvation
is far better
than the suffering
is bad.
I think Paul's confidence
in this truth
comes from his understanding
of what suffering is
and where it comes from
and what glory,
what future salvation is
and where it comes from.
And as we have established
in my introduction
this morning,
we all in here
know what suffering is,
although we might have
different ideas
about where it comes from.
I think most of us
in this room
are a bit fuzzier
on the term glory.
Is that fair to say?
Okay.
A bit fuzzier
on the term glory.
Many of us
who grew up in the church
we probably know
where it comes from
even if we don't know
exactly what it is.
But what I want to do
with the rest of our time
as we unpack this passage
in Romans 8
is I want to define glory.
What is it
and where does it come from?
Specifically in this passage
and what is suffering
and where does it come from?
And I think,
I hope,
that if I do
a halfway decent job
you might be convinced
of Paul's thesis statement
that our present sufferings
are not worthy
to be compared
to the future glory
that is in Christ.
So, first thing
I want us to notice
is that Paul situates
sufferings and glory
as opposites
in this passage.
They are opposite experiences.
Present suffering
and future glory
are opposed
to one another.
Glory,
it's a mysterious
and somewhat religious word
that we don't really use
very often
in our normal
everyday vocabulary.
It can be a hard word
to define.
It's used multiple ways
in the Bible
to talk about
the visible expression
of God's holiness,
brilliance,
and beauty.
Even if you didn't
grow up in church,
probably the most famous time
that you might think
about this phrase,
we all grew up hearing
the Christmas story.
The angels appeared
to the shepherds
and it says,
the glory of the Lord
shone round about them.
The KJV,
we remember that?
All right.
Glory,
it's this visible expression.
It's us,
it's human beings
grasping for a word
to explain
the visible brilliance
of God's beauty
when it shows up
on earth,
when we can see it,
when we can get
a glimpse of it,
we come up
with this word,
glory.
And using some context clues
from the rest
of the passage today,
I would say
that what Paul means
when he talks about
future glory
is this.
Glory is the ultimate
visible expression
of all of creation
under God's rule
and reign.
It is the visible thing
that we can see
when God is in charge
the way that he was
intended to be in charge,
when all of creation
falls under submission
to God.
The only thing
that we will experience,
the thing that we will see
is glory.
It is beauty.
It is life
as it was intended
to be.
So glory
is the visible
expression
of all of creation
under God's rule
and reign.
Suffering,
on the other hand,
as you might have guessed
since there are opposites,
suffering is the visible
expression
of creation
under our rule
and reign.
And death
is its ultimate
expression.
So,
Genesis 1,
beginning of the book,
we remember this.
God created everything
and it was good
and very good.
All that we knew
was glory,
the visible expression
of creation
as it was intended
to be.
and a few pages
in humanity
decided to rebel
against God.
We didn't want to live
under his rule
or reign.
We didn't trust
that he was good,
that he had good plans
for his creation.
And from that moment
on,
all we see
throughout Scripture,
throughout human history,
throughout my life experience,
and I'm sure
your life experience,
is suffering
suffering
after suffering
after suffering,
broken relationships,
financial struggles,
sickness,
war.
Suffering
is the visible expression
of all of creation
under our rule
and reign
and all of our suffering
is heading
to one climactic moment
that every single one
of us in the room
tries very hard
to avoid thinking about
and that is death.
none of us
are going to get away
from it.
I was at JD's
with Rory
and my nephew Grayson
a couple,
like a week ago
and I went up
with my nephew Grayson
on one of the slides
and I'm not a heights person.
We all know
I'm not a heights person.
And so like
I'm trying to be brave.
I mean it's a kid slide,
right?
And I'm like
with my nephew
and there's this kid
in front of us in line
and he's like,
are you alright?
I'm like,
no.
He's like probably
nine or ten
kind of like
cocky sports kid
and he's like,
you're scared?
And I said,
yeah,
I'm a little bit scared.
He's like,
I'm not scared.
I'm not scared of anything.
And he starts like
puffing up his chest
and like comparing himself
to me and I'm like,
whoa man,
like we don't need to
do this right now.
We really don't need
to do this right now.
And he starts listing
things that he's not scared of.
I'm not scared of snakes.
I'm not scared of spiders.
And he literally
is like going down this list.
And I was like,
well that's cool.
Yeah,
I'm trying to like
keep conversation.
We're waiting in line
and all of a sudden
it gets quiet.
And he goes,
I am scared to die.
I'm like,
yeah man,
that makes sense,
right?
It's the ultimate
conclusion
of all of our
suffering on earth
and none of us
can avoid it
and most of us
don't really know
what to do with it.
What's going to happen?
What is this
whole thing about?
And what Paul
is going to say
throughout his writings
is that death
is the ultimate
expression
of what happens
when we take control.
When we remove God
from the equation,
death is the final
consequence
of our rebellion.
In the beginning,
when God created,
everything was good
and very good.
His glory was all
that was seen
or known.
We rebel
and from that moment forward
all we know
is suffering
that leads
to death.
Because all of creation
is no longer
as God intended it
to be,
creation under God's
rule and reign
was good
and very good
but when we chose
to rule for ourselves
what the Bible says
is that God
actually just allows us
to suffer the consequences
of our decisions.
When we think about wrath,
we think about God's wrath,
we think about God
being angry
and punishing us
but ultimately
as you read the Scriptures
what God's wrath is
is Him allowing us
to experience
the consequences
of our decisions.
Like when we rebelled,
the consequence,
He said it very clearly,
you will surely die.
He let out the boundaries,
He set the system up,
we rebelled
and He says,
okay,
you can have
that decision,
you can rule and reign
but what's going to happen
because of that decision
are these consequences,
all of creation.
has been impacted
and N.T. Wright says
that creation
is out of joint.
Let's read it
in verse 19.
He says,
for the creation,
this is not humanity,
this is the earth,
all of creation
waits in eager expectation
for the children of God
to be revealed.
For the creation,
the earth,
was subject to frustration
not by its own choice
but by the will
of the one
who subjected it
in hope.
that the creation itself
will be liberated
from its bondage
to decay
and brought into
freedom and glory
of the children
of God.
We know
that the whole creation
has been groaning
as in the pains
of childbirth
right up to the present time.
Not only so
but we ourselves
who have the first fruits
of the spirit
grown inwardly
as we wait eagerly
for our adoption
to sonship.
The redemption,
listen to this,
the redemption
of our bodies.
The result
of our rebellion
against God
didn't just negatively
affect us
but Paul says
it negatively affected
all of creation.
Creation is frustrated
and subject
to futility.
We were intended.
God's glory
was our,
his intention
was us to be stewards
under creation,
over creation
under God's rule
and reign
and instead
we took charge
in all of creation
including ourselves
as paying
the consequences.
everything
immediately became
more difficult
and dangerous
when prior
to the rebellion
nothing was dangerous
or difficult.
Verse 20 says
that the earth
is dying
and I would say
that we are probably
accelerating the process.
It doesn't mean
that all of creation
is not beautiful
or good.
It's that it's
out of joint.
It's suffering
the consequences
of our sin.
I had the opportunity
to go to Wyoming
about a year ago.
It's like
one of the most
beautiful places
I've ever been.
So incredible.
Like mountains
and rivers
and we're going
on hikes
and I'm just like
blown away
by the scenery,
by the majesty,
by the beauty
of creation
but then
every once in a while
it hit me.
I am exposed
out here.
Right?
Like if I was out
by myself
there was a group
of us like
bear,
snake,
rock slide,
like there's
a number
of things
that could
take me out
in an instant.
I am maybe
not made
for Wyoming.
I don't know
if you can tell
or not.
But this is
the reality
of the creation
that we live in.
It is beautiful
and yet chaotic.
There are shadows
of God's glory
and his beauty
and yet it is
filled with the
consequences
of our rebellion.
Not only is
creation groaning
but he says
we also
those of us
who have
experienced
God's goodness
who have
received the
Holy Spirit
who understand
that there's
a better plan
for the future.
Those of us
who have tasted
that we understand
that there's
a better hope
for the future
and therefore
we groan
in the midst
of our present
circumstances
because we know
that life
is not
as it should
be.
And if you
don't have
that hope
if you don't
have that
worldview
if this is
all there is
there's no
reason to groan
there's no reason
it's just
accept it
this life
is what it is
there's nothing
that's going
to change
but those
of us
who have
accepted
the resurrection
of Jesus
Christ
we believe
that life
is not
as it should
be
and so
Paul says
we groan
all of our
suffering
is a result
of broken
creation
or broken
humanity
our broken
relationships
are either
because we're
selfish
or the other
person is selfish
or likely
both
financial struggles
are often
because of greed
fear
anxiety
worry
addiction
sickness
cancer
miscarriages
infertility
all results
of a broken
creation
all results
of suffering
because we
took charge
all leading
to the ultimate
expression
of suffering
which is death
none of these
things existed
in creation
prior to our
rebellion
and God
is redeeming
and ultimately
will redeem
all of creation
for his glory
and for our good
this is the hope
of our future
salvation
so what
should we
smile
and pretend
like everything's
great
we got
salvation
coming
so
it is what
it is
right
get the
coffee
mugs
with the
chippy verses
put the
bumper stickers
on
pretend like
all of
suffering
on this
earth
is not
a big
deal
yes
no
we know
that all
of creation
is groaning
not only so
but we
ourselves
who have
the first
fruits of the
spirit
we groan
inwardly
Paul says
groan
weep
mourn
lament
the life
we are
experiencing
on earth
is not
as God
intended it
to be
my first
application point
for us
this morning
as followers
of Jesus
in the midst
of suffering
is to
lament
the fracture
mourn
lament
weep
the fact
that creation
is fractured
this honors
God
he laments
with us
when we
lament
the brokenness
of this world
we are
aligning
our view
with his
view
he knows
creation
is not
as it
is intended
to be
he is in
the process
of restoring
and redeeming
it
and instead
often times
we who are
the source
of the problem
pretend like
we can be
the architects
of the solution
how often
do we think
that we can
fix things
on our own
no we lament
if the ultimate
climax
of all of
human suffering
is death
this is why
the gospel
of Jesus Christ
is the central
point of all
of human
history
think about
this
if literally
if the
climax
of our
rebellion
is our
death
that means
that if
Jesus rose
from the
dead
if he is
son of
God
came
lived a
perfect
life
died
on our
place
for our
sins
the central
point
in human
history
is the
resurrection
because
Jesus
proved
that he
did
the thing
he said
he did
that he
conquered
our
ultimate
enemy
that he
conquered
the
consequences
of our
ultimate
rebellion
the
God
who
made
the
whole
world
entered
the
world
and had
victory
over the
consequences
of our
rebellion
he had
the victory
that you
and I
could not
have
he did
the thing
that we
were powerless
to do
the son
of God
died
buried
and was
raised
from the
dead
his
empty
tomb
is the
proof
that he
conquered
all
of the
consequences
of our
rebellion
and the
climax
of the
consequences
of our
rebellion
is death
and he
rose
from the
dead
proving
that he
had
power
over all
of the
consequences
our future
salvation
then
is not
some
disembodied
heavenly
experience
away from
earth
what Paul
says
is the
redemption
of all
of creation
is the
redemption
of our
bodies
and the
restoration
of all
creation
the
climax
of God's
redemption
is not
to suck
us away
from here
but to
bring us
back here
to a
redeemed
earth
so that
we can
experience
life as
it was
intended
to be
this is
why it
says
creation
is waiting
for our
resurrection
why would
creation
eagerly
be waiting
to be
destroyed
it's
eagerly
being
waiting
to be
redeemed
for the
children
of God
to return
to inherit
the new
heavens
and the
new
earth
for all
of eternity
this is
why Paul
could say
I consider
it
that our
present
sufferings
are not
worthy
to be
compared
to our
future
glory
because
he had
a right
understanding
of what
suffering
is
and where
it
comes
from
and he
had a
right
understanding
of what
glory
is
and where
it
comes
from
suffering
comes
from
our
rebellion
and our
sin
glory
comes
from
God's
rule
and reign
being
restored
and Jesus
made
a way
for
our
suffering
and sin
to be
destroyed
once
and for
all
1 Corinthians
death
where is
your
victory
death
where is
your
sting
the reason
Paul can
count the
cost
can do
the
calculations
can say
that present
sufferings
aren't
worthy
to be
compared
to future
glory
is because
he has
an accurate
view
of future
glory
that is
rooted
in the
resurrection
of Jesus
if Jesus
truly rose
from the
dead
then everything
is different
see I think
the reason
why so many
Christians
struggle to
resonate
with Paul's
calculations
we read
words like
okay
present
suffering
not
worthy
to be
compared
to future
glory
and we're
like
really
our
present
suffering
feels
pretty
bad
and I've
heard
pastors
talk
about
heaven
and
I'm
not
sure
it's
that
great
compared
to
what
we're
talking
about
see the
main
focus
of the
gospel
in the
American
church
has been
Jesus
dying
on the
cross
to forgive
you of
your sins
so that
you can
go to
heaven
when you
die
how many
of you
guys
have
heard
that
how many
of you
guys
think
that's
true
it
is
it's
true
don't
worry
you guys
a couple
people
almost
got up
and left
it is
true
but it's
a relatively
small part
of the
story
see the
focal point
of the
redemptive
story
is not
the cross
and forgiveness
but the
empty tomb
and the
resurrection
of God's
children
to inherit
the new
heaven
and the
new
earth
God
didn't
give up
on his
original
creation
he's
not
taking us
away
somewhere
to live
forever
he's
taking us
away
somewhere
temporarily
to be
absent
with the
bodies
to be
present
with the
Lord
that's
true
but he
is going
to bring
us
back
he's
going
to redeem
all
of
creation
he's
going
to make
things
as they
were
intended
to be
God
did not
give up
on his
original
plan
the
resurrection
proves
God's
redemption
for all
of
creation
this is
what Paul
and what
all of
creation
are eagerly
anticipating
is the
return
of the
resurrected
Christ
the
resurrection
judgment
of the
dead
and the
bringing
of heaven
back to
a
redeemed
earth
I love
how a
pastor
named Matt
Bowen
says it
he said
a disembodied
bliss
is not
what you
were created
for
heaven
would be a
mere
consolation
to the
life we've
lost
or never
had
but
resurrection
is the
restoration
of the
life we've
lost
never
had
the
ultimate
destination
for
followers
of
Jesus
is not
to be
absent
from the
good
beautiful
and
God
honoring
experiences
we have
on earth
but to be
filled with
them for
all of
eternity
without any
possibility
of sin
suffering
or rebellion
ever entering
into creation
again because
all of us
who will
inherit
the new
heavens
and the
new
earth
have
bowed
our
knee
to
Jesus
there
is
no
more
opportunity
for
rebellion
and so
Paul can
say
present
sufferings
have
nothing
to be
compared
to our
future
glory
because
he's
tasted
and seen
broken
beauty
on earth
and he
knows
that it
will be
perfect
and fulfilled
the new
heavens
and the
new
earth
I love
how John
Piper
says it
he gave
this quote
to children
but I
think most
of us
are children
at heart
so we
can
appreciate
this
he says
that the
new
heavens
of the
new
earth
are the
hope
of the
future
glory
you
will
have
the
best
body
imaginable
can
anybody
say
amen
I went
to the
gym
this
morning
it's
not
looking
good
you
will
have
the
best
body
imaginable
there
will
be
playing
and
climbing
swimming
and
running
jumping
and
swinging
skiing
and
roller
skating
and
skateboarding
biking
and
hiking
bouncing
and
tumbling
hopping
and
whatever
else
you
do
when
you
are
very
happy
resurrection
yes
Jesus
died
to
forgive
you
of
your
sins
that
is
true
but
he
rose
again
to
redeem
all
of
creation
and
to
resurrect
us
to
a
new
heaven
and
a
new
earth
we
will
experience
the
beauty
of
earth
as
it
was
intended
to
be
we
will
see
God's
glory
present
invisible
for
all
eternity
if
you're
a
follower
of
Jesus
lament
the
fracture
of
creation
and
look
to
the
future
of
the
hope
of
the
resurrection
Romans 8
and
Paul
says
for
this
hope
we
were
saved
but
hope
that
is
seen
no
hope
at
all
who
hopes
for
what
they
have
already
seen
but
if
we
hope
for
what
we
do
not
yet
have
we
wait
for
it
patiently
Paul
saying
yeah
you're
going to
experience
suffering
here
on
this
earth
you're
not
going
to
fully
experience
the
future
glory
but
the
resurrection
of
Jesus
Christ
is
the
down
payment
and if
we
believe
that
if
we
hold
on
to
that
we
can
know
with
confident
expectation
that's
the
biblical
word
for
hope
not
I
wish
it
happens
I
hope
it
might
happen
confident
expectation
that
all
of
creation
will
be
redeemed
in
Christ
children
will
be
resurrected
so
if you're
in here
you're a follower
of Jesus
if you've
based
your life
placed
your faith
in
Jesus
Christ
died
buried
risen
again
just
encourage
you
with
these
words
I'm
not
going
to
even
try
and
make
it
better
than
what
Paul
says
I
consider
that
our
present
sufferings
are
not
worth
comparing
with
the
glory
that
will
be
revealed
lament
the
fracture
of
this
creation
life
is not
as it
should
be
your
suffering
is not
God's
will
for
your
life
lament
the
fracture
and then
enjoy
the
shadows
of the
beauty
that
you
experience
on
earth
I
made
a
pretty
depressing
case
for
all
of
creation
right
but we
know
we
experience
it
we
see
beautiful
things
we
go on
walks
with our
family
we have
a good
cup
of coffee
in the
morning
I'm
trying to
think of
the things
that I
can say
enjoy
that you
won't
judge
me
for
we
fish
we hike
we bike
we run
we do
all of
these
wonderful
beautiful
things
when we
enjoy
the beauty
of
creation
even
in the
midst
of
its
brokenness
we
worship
God
we
give
him
thanks
and we
know
that what
we see
in part
now
we will
ultimately
see
fully
for all
of
eternity
so we
lament
the
brokenness
when
suffering
comes
into
this
world
we
lament
it
when
the
media
cycle
of
November
comes
along
we
lament
it
when
nations
rage
and war
against
nations
when
doctors
give
diagnosis
when
the
pregnancy
test
comes
back
not
pregnant
again
when
loved
ones
pass
we
lament
grieve
but
not
as
people
without
hope
lament
the
fracture
look
to
the
future
enjoy
the
shadows
of
creation
if
you're
in
here
you're
not
a
follower
of
Jesus
the
pain
and
suffering
that
you
experience
in
this
present
world
does
not
have
to
the
final
word
again
I'm
going
to
summarize
C.S.
Lewis
and so
it's
going to
sound
less
smart
than
it
sounds
when
he
says
it
but
C.S.
Lewis
says
there's
really
three
ways
to
approach
suffering
and
a
lack
of
satisfaction
on
this
earth
he
says
there's
the
fool's
way
when
the
marriage
doesn't
give you
the
satisfaction
that
you
think
it
will
you
go
find
another
marriage
when
the
job
doesn't
give
you
the
satisfaction
you
think
it
would
you
find
another
job
when
the
hobby
when
the
pleasure
whatever
it is
you keep
chasing
pleasure
you keep
going
to
the
next
thing
and
the
next
thing
and
eventually
you
think
you'll
find
satisfaction
but
if
you've
done
that
for
long
enough
at
all
you
know
it
doesn't
work
C.S.
Lewis
says
that
there's
the
fool
and
then
often
the
fool
turns
to
the
cynic
because
he's
tried
she's
they've
gone
to
the
next
thing
and
the
next
thing
and
the
next
thing
and
it
still
leaves
them
empty
and
unsatisfied
so
he
says
the
cynic
just
becomes
comfortable
with
well
I
guess
this
is
as
good
it
gets
I
guess
these
experiences
are the
best
they'll
be
I'll
constantly
be
thirsting
and
hungering
for
more
and
so
I
just
will
stop
expecting
much
out
of
this
life
then
he
says
there's
the
Christian
way
the
Christian
way
realizes
that
the
world
is
actually
broken
and
in
need
of
redemption
and
that's
the
reason
that
nothing
can
fully
satisfy
us
on
earth
it's
because
our
deepest
longings
can
only
be
filled
in
creation
under
God's
rule
and
reign
it
all
comes
down to
what
we do
with
the
resurrection
if
Jesus
raised
from
the
dead
everything
is
different
Paul
literally
says
this
in
Corinthians
to
Christians
he says
if
Jesus
didn't
raise
from
the
dead
we
are
a
people
to
be
most
pitied
says
go
eat
and
drink
try
and
find
satisfaction
do
your
best
because
if
Christ
didn't
rise
from
the
dead
then
really
our
only
two
options
are
the
fool
or
the
cynic
I
think
Paul
suggests
the
fool
he's
like
go ahead
and try
it
look
for it
so if
you're in
here
and you've
never
wrestled
with the
claims
of Jesus
raising
from
the
dead
I'd
invite
you
to
consider
those
this
morning
in
my
opinion
in
my
view
it
is
the
only
true
good
way
to
face
suffering
and
to
face
the
question
of
that
kid
on
the
slide
at
JD's
scared
to
die
yeah
apart
from
the
resurrection
we
all
should
be
scared
to
die
but
because
of
the
resurrection
of
Jesus
Christ
which
is
historically
noteworthy
to say
the least
if that
happened
we don't
have to
be afraid
and if
it didn't
happen
I'm
wasting
a lot
of time
so
I hope
if you're
in here
you're not
a follower
of Jesus
that you'd
find
somebody
that you
have a
relationship
with
that you
could
talk
to
about
the
hope
of
the
resurrection
for
those
of us
that are
followers
of
Jesus
I hope
that we
get a
more
full
picture
of our
salvation
in the
future
tense
next
I
got to
clarify
because
I feel
like
I made
it sound
like
heaven's
bad
not
it's
way
better
than
here
it's
just
not
as
good
what's
coming
afterwards
life
after
death
life
after
death
for
the
follower
of
Jesus
is
good
but
what
Paul
means
when he
talks
about
future
restoration
it's
life
after
death
resurrected
Christ
bringing
the new
heavens
and the
new
earth
redeeming
all of
creation
and allowing
us to
experience
everything
as it
was
intended
to
be
let's
pray
father
we thank
you so
much
for the
hope
the
resurrection
of
Jesus
pray for
each
person
in this
room
who is
currently
experiencing
suffering
I pray
that they'd
have hope
in the
midst
of their
suffering
whether
it's due
to broken
creation
or their
own
brokenness
or the
of somebody
else
or a
combination
of the
three
God
may they
have
hope
in the
midst
of their
suffering
may they
lament
the
brokenness
of this
creation
and look
forward
to the
hope
of future
new
creation
father we
are so
so grateful
that you
give us
another
option
that we
don't have
to be
the fool
or the
cynic
God that we
can enjoy
the good
things
of this
creation
knowing
that it's
broken
and better
things are
to come
may we
live in
light of
that
every day
for your
glory
and for
our good
it's in
Jesus name
I pray
amen
we are
going to
end this
morning
by a
reading
from
Revelation
chapter
I said
it plural
it's
Revelation
sorry
chapter 21
and 22
as we
go I'd
invite you to
just consider
the beauty
of John's
poetic
expression
of what
Paul talked
about when he
said
the present
sufferings are
not worthy to be
compared to the
future glory
he says
then I saw a
new heaven
and a new
earth
for the first
heaven and the
first earth
had passed
away and there
was no longer
any sea
I saw the
holy city
the new
Jerusalem
coming down
out of heaven
from God
prepared as a
bride beautifully
dressed for her
husband
and I heard
a loud voice
from this
throne saying
look God's
dwelling place
is now among
the people
and he will
dwell with
them
they will be
his people
and God
himself will
be their
God
he will
wipe away
every tear
from their
eyes
there will
be no more
death
or mourning
or crying
or pain
or suffering
for the old
order of things
the things
under our
rule and
reign have
passed away
he who was
seated on the
throne said
I am making
everything new
he said
write this down
for these words
are trustworthy
and true
it is done
I am the
alpha and
the omega
the beginning
and the end
to the thirsty
I will give
water without
cost from the
spring of the
water of life
those who are
victorious
will inherit
all of this
and I will be
their God
and they will
be my children
he goes on
he says
in the
new Jerusalem
he says
I did not
see a temple
in the city
for a Jewish
person
this would
be a problem
why
did I not
see a temple
because the
Lord God
Almighty
and the
Lamb
are its
temple
we need
no temple
to come
between us
and God
when God
is here
among us
the city
does not
need
the sun
or the
moon
to shine
on it
for the
glory
of God
gives its
light
and the
Lamb
is its
lamp
the nations
will walk
by its
light
the kings
of the
earth
will bring
their splendor
into it
on no
day
will its
gates
ever be
shut
for there
will be
no night
there
the glory
and honor
of the
nations
will be
brought
into it
nothing
impure
will ever
enter it
nor will
anyone
who does
what is
shameful
or deceitful
but only
those
whose names
are written
in the
Lamb's
book of
life
then the
angel
showed me
the river
of the
water
of life
as clear
as crystal
flowing
from the
throne
of God
of the
Lamb
down the
middle
of the
great
street
of the
city
on each
side
of the
river
stood
the
tree
of life
bearing
twelve
crops
of fruit
yielding
its
fruit
every
month
and the
leaves
of the
tree
are for
the
healing
of the
nations
no longer
will there
be any
curse
the throne
of God
and the
Lamb
will be
in the
city
and his
servants
will serve
them
and they
will see
his face
and his
name
will be
on their
foreheads
and there
will be
no more
night
they will
not need
the light
of a
lamp
or the
light
of the
sun
for the
Lord
will
give
them
light
and they
will reign
forever
and ever
amen
you're
dismissed
church
go in
peace
thank you
so much
yeah
that was
amazing
thank you so much
Thank you.